I don't know about you, but this
headline isn't altogether intuitive
considering that coffee generally
contains caffeine, which certainly has
an effect on our heart. Good thing my
expectations are not moored in what I
feel, but rather sway in the bewitching
call of data. I'm talking about a brand
spanking new study looking at the
relationship between coffee consumption
and a heart condition called atrial
fibrillation. In fact, this atrial
fibrillation is quite common with
millions and millions dealing with it.
In simple terms, it's a funky heart
rhythm. In longer terms, it's where the
top chambers of your heart that allow
blood from the top to drop down to the
bottom chambers of your heart don't
function normally.
There's certainly longer explanations
getting into the electrical activity of
the heart and beyond, but all you need
to know is that the top section of the
heart doesn't function uniformly. It
doesn't function as it's supposed to,
which raises the risk of clots forming
leading to stroke, and this fibrillation
can also lead to heart failure. So,
not good. So, the researchers took two
groups of people.
I made that sound more sinister than it
needed to be. They recruited, it's not
like they kidnapped hundreds of people.
They recruited and randomly assigned 200
people to either consume coffee or
abstain from coffee. Then, they tracked
the number of atrial fibrillation events
that occurred through a bunch of
techniques, some in-clinic and some
day-to-day devices, even something as
simple as an Apple Watch. Now, I'll
return to this because there is an issue
here that I'd like to get into in more
depth. For now, we know the setup. What
happened over the next 6 months then?
Well, look for yourself. The vertical
axis indicates the risk of atrial
fibrillation based on the number of
recorded events. So, if the lines go up,
that's a greater risk, a bad thing. Now,
the horizontal axis is time passed, and
the two lines, as you can see, indicate
the two groups, so coffee drinkers and
those forced into an uncaffeinated life
of barbarism, the abstinent. Clearly,
from the get-go, those who stopped
drinking coffee almost immediately had
greater risk of AFib. That's atrial
fibrillation, but I'm abbreviating it to
fit in with the youth. No one says the
full words to anything anymore. It's not
in vogue. So, the main point here is
that AFib risk is reduced when consuming
coffee. Like I said, not exactly
expected for me, but here we are. Now,
there are some things to consider, some
of which that the researchers pointed
out, too. For example, when randomized
control trials are done, the researchers
will also measure the baseline
differences between the groups to see if
there are any initial differences that
might skew the study one way or another.
Now, unfortunately, in this study, the
coffee-consuming group included more
people who had AFib ablation, which
means that the heart undergoes a
procedure that essentially kills a small
section of the heart to prevent this
defunct electrical signal from
continuing. Now, obviously, if you have
more people that have had surgery to
eliminate or lessen the number of
fibrillation episodes that they have,
can we really credit coffee for being
this magical elixir that protects
against AFib?
Hard pass. Miss me with that.
The same is true in the opposite
direction. So, more people in non-coffee
consuming group had a specific type of
atrial fibrillation. So, now we have two
uneven factors that put coffee consuming
group in a favorable position
independent of their coffee consumption.
The key takeaway here is that the study
had some flaws that we need to address.
Now, we can do that after the fact
through what are known as a statistical
adjustments. Essentially, we redo the
analysis that we just saw, so this one,
but we mathematically hold two issues,
so ablation and the type of fibrillation
constant, thereby leveling the playing
field. And here are the results. Here,
the red line dot indicate the results
once the adjustments have been made. And
if they fall to the left of the yellow
line, it in it indicates a reduced risk
of atrial fibrillation. So, this means
that the previous results stand even
when correcting for the issues in the
data.
So, great news for coffee drinkers, but
I'd like to get into a bit more
important information along with why
coffee has this effect before we finish
this out. And before that, if you're
interested in understanding if age, sex,
AFib seriousness, and atrial flutter
affect what we're going over here, then
be sure to check out the extended
version of this video that you're
watching, or you can always check out
the article that comes along with all of
my videos. And you get all these perks
right here over here. I'm actually going
on almost 2 years releasing a monthly
podcast that covers many topics on many
investigations, all science-based and
all focused on applicable takeaways. You
get access to all of that that I just
said, including live sessions with me
and more as a Physionic Insider. Check
it out and see if it's for you. The link
to join is in the description box. So,
good news, but how is this supposed to
have worked? Well, it's not entirely
clear, but the researchers point out a
few possibilities, like some previous
research pointing to adenosine molecules
that are secreted by our cells
throughout the day at increasing
concentrations bind to our atrial cells.
Those are heart cells that are involved
in atrial fibrillation using a receptor
on the cell surface. When it binds, it
encourages a series of proteins inside
the cell to bind potassium channels in
the cell membrane. These potassium
channels are critical for proper
electrical signaling, exactly what we're
talking about here with atrial
fibrillation. And these signaling
proteins activated by adenosine bound to
the receptor will open the potassium
channel, disrupting the normal function
of this potassium channel by prematurely
shortening the recharge time of the
electrical signal.
Okay, why does this matter in the terms
of coffee?
Because caffeine in coffee, as is well
known, is very molecularly similar to
adenosine, meaning that it can also bind
these adenosine receptors, known as
competitive binding.
In doing so, it stops adenosine from
enacting its cellular role, in this
case, a good thing. Now, I'm happy to go
more into this if you're interested, but
the bottom line is the caffeine molecule
protects from irregular electrical
signaling in the heart. Keep in mind,
there are other proposed mechanisms that
make coffee unique, like its polyphenol
content, but I'll leave those details
for another time. Now, the final three
points that I want to make sure that
you're aware of are: one, these results
are exclusively in people who have a
history of atrial fibrillation.
That's not to say that coffee doesn't
have other benefits for everyone else,
but for this context, we're talking
about a special population, though a
relatively common one. And two, the
researchers' assessment of atrial
fibrillation was based on clinical
measures and day-to-day measurements,
like I mentioned before. But some of the
wearables were uneven between groups.
So, if you're using a variety of
techniques and one group uses one system
more than the other, depending on the
quality of that system to detect AFib,
it could bias the results of one way or
another, as in fewer AFib events are
detected in one group over the other,
not because the other group doesn't have
those events, but because they weren't
detected. This is a slim possibility,
but a real one. Even the researchers
admit that limitation.
And finally,
those poor people who had to stop
consuming coffee,
only about 70% truly quit coffee for the
6 months. So, compliance was
understandably lower. However, while we
could argue that this is a negative,
it could also be a positive because it
also means that the results may be
slightly skewed in favor of the
non-coffee drinkers. And that means that
if everyone had truly quit, gone to the
absolute zero, we might have picked up
an even greater benefit. So, the fact
that a positive result was picked up
regardless is impactful. So, what are
the takeaways here? The study indicates
that if you suffer from atrial
fibrillation, there is now some evidence
that coffee is not only is not a risk
for atrial fibrillation, but reduces
your risk relative to if you abstain
from caffeinated coffee within reason.
But you know what else is a risk?
Preparing your coffee the wrong way. It
actually matters to your health. Find
out how right here. Or timing your
coffee incorrectly. That also affects
your health. Find out how right here.
Thanks for tuning in. Enjoy your coffee.
Speak with you soon.